Guide to the Edward G. Levy Collection of Papers Relating to Music
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edward G. Levy collection of papers relating to music
1859-1970
1880-1910
GEN MSS 955
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.63
(7 boxes)
Contains manuscript and printed music, and scrapbooks, photographs, printed material, and other materials relating to nineteenth-twentieth century American and European music, collected by Edward G. Levy. Four scrapbooks made by Helen D. Love Scranton, genealogist and daughter of Edward Gurley Love (1850-1919) and Lucy Cleveland Prindle, contain advertisements, programs, tickets, and manuscript notes relating to performances of opera, musicals, plays, orchestral music, chamber music, vocal recitals, children's concerts, dance, and non-Western music in New York City, Bayreuth, Berlin, Paris, and London, 1895-1910, including materials relating to the Metropolitan Opera, Carnegie Hall, the Symphony Society of New York, the Philharmonic Society of New York, German opera in New York City conducted by Walter Damrosch, the Bayreuth Festspielhaus, the Kroll Opera, and the Berliner Philharmoniker. Music includes an unidentified fragment, autograph manuscript, signed, by P. A. Tirindelli, 1894, and clippings of songs and keyboard music published in magazines, 1886-1888 and undated. Photographs include images of American singer and actress Lillian Russell, on Sweet Caporal Cigarette cards (Kinney Bros., New York), circa 1880s-1890s; and Italian actress Giannina Chiantoni, in Italian theater productions, circa 1910. Printed material includes clippings of newspaper advertisements for theater performances in the Howard Athenaeum, Boston, 1859 and undated, and the Wagner Opera House, Bradford, Pennsylvania, 1884-1885. Other materials consist of articles by Marion Thede and Harold Preece, circa 1970s, about American cowboy songs, typescript with printer's annotations, possibly published in Real West magazine; and buttons and paper fans advertisting American businesses and organizations relating to music, circa 1900.
Levy, Edward G., 1898-1990
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edward G. Levy, 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Edward G. Levy (1898-1990)
Edward G. Levy received his LL.B from Boston University in 1921 and joined his brother's New Haven law practice. In 1939 he was sentenced to a year in jail for his participation in a kickback scheme led by the mayor of Waterbury. In later years he and his wife, Hortense R. Levy, collected autographs and dime novels and made substantial donations of these materials to several libraries. Edward G. Levy died in 1990.
Scope and Contents
Contains manuscript and printed music, and scrapbooks, photographs, printed material, and other materials relating to 19th-20th century American and European music, collected by Edward G. Levy. Four scrapbooks made by Helen D. Love Scranton, genealogist and daughter of Edward Gurley Love (1850-1919) and Lucy Cleveland Prindle, contain advertisements, programs, tickets, and manuscript notes relating to performances of opera, musicals, plays, orchestral music, chamber music, vocal recitals, children's concerts, dance, and non-Western music in New York City, Bayreuth, Berlin, Paris, and London, 1895-1910, including materials relating to the Metropolitan Opera, German opera in New York City conducted by Walter Damrosch, Carnegie Hall, the Symphony Society of New York, the Philharmonic Society of New York, the Bayreuth Festspielhaus, the Kroll Opera, and the Berliner Philharmoniker. Music includes an unidentified fragment, autograph manuscript, signed, by P. A. Tirindelli, 1894, and clippings of songs and keyboard music published in magazines, 1886-1888 and undated. Photographs include images of American singer and actress Lillian Russell, on Sweet Caporal Cigarette cards (Kinney Bros., New York), circa 1880s-1890s; and Italian actress Giannina Chiantoni, in Italian theater productions, circa 1910. Printed material includes clippings of newspaper advertisements for theater performances in the Howard Athenaeum, Boston, 1859 and undated, and the Wagner Opera House, Bradford, Pennsylvania, 1884-1885. Other materials consist of articles by Marion Thede and Harold Preece, circa 1970s, about American cowboy songs, typescript with printer's annotations, possibly published in Real West magazine; and buttons and paper fans advertisting American businesses and organizations relating to music, circa 1900.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Helen D. Love Scranton Scrapbooks, 1895-1910. II. Music, 1886-1894. III. Photographs, 1880s-1949. IV. Printed Material, 1859-1970s. V. Other Materials, 1900-1970s.
Cowboys -- Songs and music; Piano music; Songs with piano; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century; Buttons (information artifacts) -- United States -- 20th Century; Fans (costume accessories) -- United States -- 20th Century; Cigarette cards -- United States -- 19th century; Photographs -- Italy -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Chiantoni, Giannina, 1881-1972 -- Portraits; Damrosch, Walter, 1862-1950; Levy, Edward G., 1898-1990; Preece, Harold, 1906-; Russell, Lillian, 1861-1922 -- Portraits; Scranton, Helen D. Love (Helen Douglas Love), 1879-1968; Thede, Marion; Tirindelli, P. A. (Pier Adolfo), 1858-1937; Berliner Philharmoniker; Carnegie Hall (New York, N.Y.); Festspielhaus (Bayreuth, Germany); Howard Athenaeum; Kinney Bros; Krolloper; Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.); Philharmonic Society of New York; Symphony Society of New York; Wagner Opera House (Bradford, Pa.)
- Helen D. Love Scranton Scrapbooks, 1895-1910; Series I; 1; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Scrapbook, 1895-1902 (Box 1 (Oversize))
    Scope and Contents
    Contains materials relating to music and theater in New York City
  - Scrapbook, 1897-1906 (Box 2 (Oversize))
    Contains materials relating to German opera conducted by Walter Damrosch, 1897, and other music and theater in New York City, 1902-1906
  - Scrapbook, 1902-1906 (Box 3 (Oversize))
    Contains materials relating to music and theater in Bayreuth, Berlin, Paris, and London, 1902-1903, and in New York City, 1903-1906
    Ownership inscription of Helen D. Love Scranton
  - Scrapbook, 1907-1910 (Box 4 (Oversize))
- Music, 1886-1894; Series II; 0.14; (0.33 box)
  - Tirindelli, P. A. (Pier Adolfo). Unidentified fragment, autograph manuscript, signed, 1894 June 24 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Music for voice and piano. Clippings, 1886, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    From The Young Ladies Journal (London)
  - Music for voice and piano. Clippings, 1888, undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 18)
    From The Young Ladies Journal (London) and Waverley Magazine and Literary Repository (Boston)
  - Other printed music, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1880s-1949; Series III; 0.14; (0.33 box)
  - Russell, Lillian, [1880s-1890s?] (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Photographs on Sweet Caporal Cigarette cards (Kinney Bros., New York)
  - Chiantoni, Giannina, [circa 1910?] (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Photographs of Chiantoni in Italian theater productions
  - Unidentified, 1939-1949, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Printed Material, 1859-1970s; Series IV; 0.14; (0.33 box)
  - Clippings, 1859-1885, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Includes advertisements for theater performances in the Howard Athenaeum, Boston, 1859 and undated; and the Wagner Opera House, Bradford, Pennsylvania, 1884-1885
  - Other printed material, 1881-1970s, undated; 5 (Box 5, Folder 8-12)
  - Other printed material, 1893-1969, undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 19)
- Other Materials, 1900-1970s; Series V; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Thede, Marion, and Preece Harold. "The Story Behind the Song," articles, typescript wth revisions and printers annotations, [1970s?]; 2 (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
    Possibly published in Real West magazine
  - Objects, [circa 1900]; 3 (Box 6, Folder 15-17)